Guide to the Eric Alfred Havelock Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Eric Alfred Havelock papers
1903-2000
MS 1489
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
39.25
The papers consist of correspondence; topical files; writings; research materials; lecture and course notes; and departmental files documenting the professional career of classicist Eric A. Havelock as educator, administrator, and author. His political interests and activities during his years in Canada are also represented. Autobiographical materials and family photographs are included in the papers.
Havelock, Eric Alfred, 1903-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Christine M. Havelock, 1988, 1990, and 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 62, Series VI is restricted until January 1, 2040
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. Correspondence, 1931-2000. II. Professional Files, 1946-1988. III. Canadian Files, 1925-1980. IV. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1903-1989. V. Writings, Research, and Teaching Files, 1930s-1988. VI. Yale Classics Department Files, 1932-1971.
Biographical / Historical
Eric Alfred Havelock was born in London, England, on June 3, 1903, the son of Alfred H. and Annie Louise (Williams) Havelock. As a young boy, he lived in Scotland, attending Greenock Academy where he was introduced to Greek at age twelve. From 1917 to 1926, he was at Cambridge, first at Leys, an English public school, where he studied under W. H. Balgarnie, a classics professor after whom James Hilton's Mr. Chips was created. In 1922 Havelock won a scholarship to Emmanuel College, Cambridge University, and graduated in 1926 with distinctions in the classical tripos and ancient philosophy.
Migrating to Canada, Havelock served as assistant and associate professor at Acadia University in Nova Scotia from 1926 to 1929 and was an associate professor at Victoria College at the University of Toronto from 1929 to 1947. In addition to his academic responsibilities, he pursued outside political interests. A former member of the British Labour Party, Havelock continued his participation in the liberal cause and was active in local politics. He was a founding member of the League for Social Reconstruction in 1930 and was elected to the provincial council and executive committee of the Co-operative Commonwealth Federation (CCF) which merged with the Canadian Labour Congress in 1961, emerging as the New Democratic Party. In 1945, he ran unsuccessfully as a CCF candidate for the constituency of South Wellington to the Ontario legislature. He was also the associate editor of the Canadian Forum. On the academic front, he was a Guggenheim Fellow in 1941 and 1943 and co-founded the Ontario Classical Association, parent organization of the Canadian Classical Association, in 1944, serving as its first president and associate editor of its publication, The Phoenix.
In 1947, Havelock moved to Cambridge, Massachussetts, to assume academic posts at Harvard University: senior tutor in Leverett House (1947-1950), associate and full professor of Greek and Latin (1947-1963), chairman of the Classics Department (1956-1961), and acting chairman in 1962. He was a member of the Harvard Committee on Admissions and Scholarships (1948- 1963), and a member of the Board of Trustees of Radcliffe College (1959-1963). During this time, he assisted in the drafting of the recommendation that female students receive a joint degree with Harvard. He also participated in the formation of the proposal establishing the Center for Hellenic Studies in Washington, D.C. and was a senior fellow on the governing board (1965-1973).
Visiting professorships at Princeton University (1961-1963) preceded Havelock's appointment as Sterling Professor of Classics at Yale University (1963-1971) and chairman of the Classics Department (1963-1969). Upon his retirement from Yale in 1971, Havelock was the Raymond Distinguished Professor of Classics at the State University of New York, Buffalo (1971-1973).
Havelock lectured at numerous North American and European academic institutions and was the author of numerous scholarly articles and books: The Lyric Genius of Catullus (1939), The Crucifixion of Intellectual Man (1950), The Liberal Temper in Greek Politics (1957), Preface to Plato (1963), The Greek Concept of Justice (1975), The Literate Revolution in Greece and Its Cultural Consequences (1983), The Muse Learns to Write (1987), War as a Way of Life in Classical Culture (Vanier Lecture), Prologue to Greek Literacy (Semple Lecture), and Origins of Western Literacy. He was co-editor with Yale English professor Maynard Mack for the Prentice-Hall Greek Drama Series (1970-1973) and with Jackson Hershbell for Communication Arts in the Ancient World (1978).
Havelock married Ellen Parkinson in 1927, and had a daughter, Joan Ellen (Mrs. Richard Wheeler-Bennett), two sons, John Eric and Ronald Geoffrey, and ten grandchildren. In 1962, he married Christine Mitchell, professor of art at Vassar College and author of Hellinistic Art. Havelock died at his home in Poughkeepsie, New York, on April 4, 1988, after a short illness.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence; topical files; writings; research materials; lecture and course notes; and departmental files documenting the professional career of classicist Eric A. Havelock as educator, administrator, and author. His political interests and activities during his years in Canada are also represented. Autobiographical materials and family photographs are included in the papers.
Prentice-Hall Greek drama series; Classical philology; Classicists; Havelock, Eric Alfred, 1903-; Center for Hellenic Studies (Washington, D.C.); Co-operative Commonwealth Federation; League for Social Reconstruction; Ontario Classical Association; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Classics
- Correspondence, 1931-2000; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Correspondence files are arranged in three sections: chronological, with the bulk of letters from the mid 1930s through the early 1970s; alphabetical, with emphasis on the late 1960s until Havelock's death in 1988, with some overlap between the two sections; and publishers. The letters often mix personal and professional communication, demonstrating Havelock's gift for maintaining relationships over the years, and in some cases, for decades, with students, colleagues, and associates. His correspondence, while concentrated in this series, may be found in lesser degrees throughout the remaining series.
  The Publishers files of correspondence are arranged alphabetically by name of publisher, publication, or literary agent and document Havelock's role as a contributor and/or editorial advisor. Although the magnitude of these files attests to Havelock's prolific authorship, the files themselves contain rather routine correspondence and accompanying materials, such as contracts; receipts and royalty statements; corrections; proofs; publicity materials; questions of copyright; and permissions to publish. Reviews of his works are included at the end of the Publishers files.
  - Chronological
    - 1935-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-23)
    - 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24-50)
    - 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 51-75)
    - 1972-1984, 1987, undated (Box 4, Folder 76-95)
  - Alphabetical
    - A, Undated (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Adrados, Francisco R., 1966-1968, 1972-1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, 1978-1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Asmis, Elizabeth, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - B, Undated (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Barros, James, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Becroft, Stephen J., 1968-1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Bowersock, Glen, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Burrage, Katharine, 1963-1964, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - C, Undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Cherniss, Harold, 1936, 1939, 1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Claus, David, 1970-1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Clausen, Wendell, 1964, 1970-1981 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Cole, A. Thomas, 1963-1968, 1983, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Cole, Michael, 1978-1983 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Cook, Albert, 1972-1978 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - D, Undated (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Dawson, Christopher, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Denver, John, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Detienne, Marcel, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - E, Undated (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Eagle, Edwin, 1936-1941, 1978-1979, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Easterling, P. E., 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Egan, Kieran, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Ellis, Alice, 1973-1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Ellis, Priscilla, 1973-1974, 1981-1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - F, Undated (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Fan mail, 1971-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 123-128)
    - Farrell, Thomas J., 1978-1982, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 129-130)
    - Feld, Marian Parry (Mrs. Maury Feld), 1971-1975, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Frye, Northrop, 1980-1987 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - G, Undated (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Garrison, Daniel H., 1974 (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Gentili, Bruno [includes Oedipus conference], 1972-1986 (Box 6, Folder 135-138)
    - Gibbs, N. [All Souls College, Oxford], 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Gill, Christopher, 1969, 1973-1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 140-144)
    - Gillis, Daniel, 1978, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - Gould, Thomas F., 1965-1969, undated (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - Grube, George and Gwyneth, 1969, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - H, Undated (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Halperin, David M., 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - Harvey, David, 1967, 1972-1974, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Hershbell, Jackson, 1962-1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 151-160)
    - Howard, M., 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Hunter, Virginia, 1978-1981, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - J, Undated (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1974-1977, 1981, undated (Box 7, Folder 164)
    - K, Undated (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Kelber, Werner, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - Kilpatrick, Ross S., 1967, 1973-1975, 1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - Kirk, Geoffrey, 1949-1950, 1966-1969, 1972-1979, 1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 168-169)
    - L, Undated (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Lloyd-Jones, Hugh, 1969-1983, undated (Box 7, Folder 171-174)
    - Lynch, John, 1970, 1972, 1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 175)
    - M, Undated (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Manville, Brook, 1979-1981, undated (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - McDiarmid, John, 1936-1941, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 178)
    - McLuhan, Marshall, 1970-1980 (Box 7, Folder 179)
    - Moskalev, Walter, 1968-1969, 1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Mothersole, Cynthia, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Mourelatos, Alexander, 1965-1978 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - Munari, Franco, 1965-1966, 1971, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - N-O, Undated (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - Natunewicz, Chester, 1973-1975, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - Ober, William B., 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Olson, Charles, 1963-1966, 1976-1980 (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - Olson, David R., 1972-1976 (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - Ong, Walter J., 1978, 1984-1988 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - Opland, Jeffrey, 1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - P, Undated (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - Packard, David, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - Page, Barbara, 1973-1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - Parkinson, Joseph, 1972-1973, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 194)
    - Parry, Adam Milman, 1958-1960, 1969-1971, undated (Box 7, Folder 195-196)
      General
      Includes Havelock's memoriam for Adam and Anne Parry.
    - Parry, Anne Amory, 1959, 1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Pfeiffer, John, 1974, 1978-1981 (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Phillips, R. J. (Jolly), 1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 199)
    - Piccolomini, Manfredi, 1978-1981 (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Postman, Neil, 1979-1982 (Box 8, Folder 201)
    - Praus-Sze, Corinne, 1967-1977 (Box 8, Folder 202-203)
    - Prier, Raymond, 1971-1979, undated (Box 8, Folder 204-205)
    - Q, Undated (Box 8, Folder 206)
    - R, Undated (Box 8, Folder 207)
    - Rexine, John, 1964, 1979-1982 (Box 8, Folder 208)
    - Richardson, Nicholas, 1972-1981 (Box 8, Folder 209)
    - Robb, Kevin, 1967-1972, 1984, undated (Box 8, Folder 210-212)
    - Rose, Peter, 1973-1980 (Box 8, Folder 213)
    - Rosenmeyer, Tom, 1944-1967, 1970-1975, 1980-1986 (Box 8, Folder 214-215)
    - S, Undated (Box 8, Folder 216)
    - Segal, Charles, 1962, 1979, undated (Box 8, Folder 217)
    - Segal, Erich, 1971-1975, 1980-1984 (Box 8, Folder 218)
    - Silk, Edmund T., 1971-1977 (Box 8, Folder 219)
    - Simon, Bennett, 1969-1972, 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 220)
    - Simpson, Michael, 1981-1982, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 221)
    - Spariosu, Mihai, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 222)
    - Stahl, Hans-Peter, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 223 - 225)
    - Stewart, Zeph, 1972-1978 (Box 8, Folder 226)
    - Sudbury, Minnie L., 1975, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 227)
    - Sullivan, John P., 1974-1986, undated (Box 8, Folder 228-230)
    - Svenbro, Jesper, 1973-1980, undated (Box 8, Folder 231)
    - T, Undated (Box 8, Folder 232)
    - Tejera, Victorino, 1985, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 233)
    - U-V, Undated (Box 9, Folder 234)
    - Underhill, Frank, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 235)
    - Vlastos, Gregory, 1938-1941, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 236)
    - Von Staden, Heinrich, 1971-1977, undated (Box 9, Folder 237)
    - W, Undated (Box 9, Folder 238)
    - Watson, A. John, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 239)
    - Weeks, Hugh, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 240)
    - West, Elinor, 1980-1985 (Box 9, Folder 241)
    - Williams, Gordon, 1973-1983 (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Z, Undated (Box 9, Folder 243)
  - Publishers
    - General [early files, projections, copyright, miscellaneous], 1931-1943, 1957-1987, undated (Box 9, Folder 244-248)
    - Agence Hoffman, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 249)
    - The Antigonish Review, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder 250)
    - Basil Blackwell Publisher, Ltd., 1938-1949, 1961-1966, 1973-1977, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 251-252)
    - Beacon Press, 1949-1962, 1965, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 253-254)
    - Cambridge University Press, 1977, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 255)
    - Chelsea House, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 256)
    - Editions La Decouverte/Maspero, 1979-1987 (Box 9, Folder 257)
    - Editorial Pomaire S. A., 1981 (Box 9, Folder 258)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1970-1974 (Box 9, Folder 259)
    - Falmer Press, 1985-1988 (Box 9, Folder 260-261)
    - Gius. Laterza & Figli, S.P.A., 1970-1985 (Box 9, Folder 262)
    - Grosset and Dunlap, Inc., 1966, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 263)
    - Hackett Publishing Company, Inc., 1978 (Box 9, Folder 264)
    - Harold Innis Foundation/Arthur Wood, 1977-1983 (Box 9, Folder 265)
    - Harold Ober Associates, Inc., 1985 (Box 9, Folder 266)
    - Harvard University Press, 1952-1987, undated (Box 10, Folder 267-276)
    - Hastings House Publishers, Inc., 1973-1987 (Box 10, Folder 277-280)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1961-1965, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 281)
    - Hudson Review, 1967, 1973-1976, 1982-1985, undated (Box 10, Folder 282-283)
    - International Encyclopedia of Communications, 1983-1988 (Box 11, Folder 284)
    - Jonathan Cape Limited, 1956-1961, 1964, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 285)
    - Journal of Communication, 1979-1980, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 286-287)
    - Labour Le Travailleur, 1980-1982, undated (Box 11, Folder 288)
    - Long Island Philosophical Society, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 289)
    - Manas, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 290)
    - Media Probes [PBS series], 1980 (Box 11, Folder 291)
    - Il Melangolo, 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 292)
    - Methuen, Inc., 1983-1985 (Box 11, Folder 293)
    - The Monist, 1980-1984 (Box 11, Folder 294-296)
    - New Literary History, 1975-1988, undated (Box 11, Folder 297-298)
    - The New Yorker, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 299)
    - Ontario Institute for Studies in Education, 1973-1979 (Box 11, Folder 300)
    - Oral English, 1969-1976, undated (Box 11, Folder 301)
    - Oral Tradition, 1984-1987 (Box 11, Folder 302)
    - Oxford University Press, 1978-1996 (Box 11, Folder 303-307)
    - Pacific Quarterly, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 308)
    - Philosophy and Rhetoric, 1976-1979 (Box 12, Folder 309)
    - Prentice-Hall, Inc.
      - Ford Humanities project, 1958-1965, undated (Box 12, Folder 310-314)
      - Greek Drama series
        - General correspondence, editorial directives, publicity, etc., 1964-1973 (Box 12, Folder 315-330)
        - Arrowsmith, William, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 331)
        - Band, Arnold J., 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 332)
        - Burnett, A. P., 1966-1970 (Box 12, Folder 333)
        - Beye, Charles, 1965-1971, undated (Box 12, Folder 334)
        - Bowra, Maurice, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 335)
        - Cavander, Kenneth, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 336)
        - Cole, Thomas, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 337)
        - Knox, Bernard, 1965-1968 (Box 13, Folder 338)
        - Lawall, Gilbert, 1965-1971 (Box 13, Folder 339)
        - Lloyd-Jones, Hugh, 1964-1968 (Box 13, Folder 340-342)
        - Mack, Maynard, 1964-1968 (Box 13, Folder 343)
        - McDiarmid, John, 1964-1969 (Box 13, Folder 344)
        - O'Connell, Paul E., 1964-1968 (Box 13, Folder 345)
        - Parry, Adam and Anne, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 346)
        - Podlecki, Anthony, 1966-1970 (Box 13, Folder 347)
        - Rose, Peter, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 348)
        - Rosenmeyer, Thomas, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 349)
        - Russo, Joseph, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 350)
        - Sale, William, 1966-1970 (Box 13, Folder 351)
        - Smith, Wesley D., 1966 (Box 13, Folder 352)
        - Wolff, Christian, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 353)
    - Presses Universitaires de France, 1977-1984 (Box 13, Folder 354)
    - Princeton University Press, 1959, 1978-1988 (Box 13, Folder 355-358)
    - Quaderni Urbinati Di Cultura Classica, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 359)
    - Russell and Russell, Inc., 1966-1976, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 360)
    - Southern Illinois University Press, 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 361)
    - SUNY Press, 1981-1983 (Box 14, Folder 362)
    - University of California Press, 1972, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 363)
    - University of Chicago Press, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 364)
    - University of Cincinnati, 1967, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 365)
    - University of Iowa [Walter Ong festschrift], 1988 (Box 14, Folder 366)
    - University of Minnesota Press, 1985-1987 (Box 14, Folder 367)
    - University of Ottawa, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 368)
    - University of Toronto Press, 1976-1977, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 369)
    - University of Washington Press, 1967-1981 (Box 14, Folder 370)
    - Visible Language, 1979-1981, undated (Box 14, Folder 371)
    - W. W. Norton and Company, 1963-1965 (Box 14, Folder 372)
    - Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, 1982-1987 (Box 14, Folder 373)
    - Written Communication Annual, 1986-1988 (Box 14, Folder 374)
    - Xin Tang, 1986-1988 (Box 14, Folder 375)
    - Yale University Press, 1944, 1956-1988 (Box 14, Folder 376-380)
    - Yale University Press, 1956-1988 (Box 15, Folder 381-382)
    - Posthumous publications and reviews [replies by Christine Havelock], 1989-2000 (Box 15, Folder 383-385)
  - Reviews of Havelock's works, 1939-1978, undated (Box 15, Folder 386-392)
- Professional Files, 1946-1988; Series II
  The Professional files are arranged in three sections: appointments, conferences, and organizations. Appointments pertain to Havelock's academic appointments at Harvard University as lecturer and professor (1947-1951), chairman of the Classics Department (1955-1960), and acting chairman (1962); member of the Board of Trustees of Radcliffe College (1959-1963); and his appointment to the Andrew Raymond Chair of Classics at the State University of New York in Buffalo (1971-1973). The files are arranged alphabetically by organization and consist of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, financial records, and printed materials. For teaching materials corresponding to Havelock's years at Harvard, consult Series V, Writings, Research, and Teaching Files. For material pertaining to his appointments at Yale University, consult Series VI, Yale Files.
  Conference files relating to the conferences and lectures attended by Havelock are arranged by the title of the event and contain primarily routine correspondence regarding logistics of the events and publicity rather than the actual lecture or paper presented.
  Materials pertaining to organizations in which Havelock participated complete the series. Of particular note is the Center for Hellenic Studies in Washington, D.C., established by the Harvard Corporation in 1960. For files on the Ontario Classical Association, of which Havelock was a co-founder and first president, consult Series III, Canadian Files.
  - Appointments
    - Harvard University/Radcliffe College
      - Admissions and Scholarship Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Classics Department [graduate studies], 1947-1963, undated (Box 16, Folder 2-5)
      - Finances, 1946-1957, 1961-1963 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Shop Club, 1962-1963, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Summer school, 1963, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Tutees/advisees, 1946-1947, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Radcliffe College [Board of Trustees], 1960-1961 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - State University of New York at Buffalo (SUNY)
      - Classics Department
        - General, 1969-1973 (Box 16, Folder 11)
        - Meeting minutes, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 12)
        - Raymond Distinguished Professor of Classics Chair, 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Vassar College
      - Davidson-Oestreich report re admission/co-education, 1967, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - "The Technology of Writing Seminar," [Alfred P. Sloan Foundation grant], 1985, 1988, undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Conferences/lectures
    - Ancient rhetorical theory [lecture at Pennsylvania State University], 1974 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - "Conversations with Eric Havelock" [University of Southern California, 1976], 1974-1976 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - "Cosmic Myths of Homer and Hesiod" [Third International Conference of Sicilian Anthropological Studies, 1981], 1981-1986 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - "Crisis in Literacy: Cultural Hard Times" [conference, Bard College Center, New York, 1981 Jan 21], 1980-1981 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - "Directions and Limits of Reflexivity on Axial Age Civilizations" [Third Axial Age Conference, includes correspondence with S. Eisenstadt, Bad Homburg, 1984 Mar], 1982-1986 (Box 16, Folder 20-21)
    - "From Homer to Plato" [lecture at Colloquium Series, Annenberg School of Communications], 1978, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - "League for Social Reconstruction: Its Economic, Political and Social Context: [discussant, University of Toronto], 1980 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - "Liberal Temper in Greek Politics" [Franconia College, New Hampshire], 1967 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - The Linguistic Task of the PreSocratics: Ionian Science in Search of an Abstract Vocabulary [public discussion, Collège de France, 1980 Mar 17], 1978-1980 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - "The Literate Revolution in Greece and its Moral Consequences" [lecture series, Ontario Institute for Studies in Education], 1973-1981, undated (Box 17, Folder 26 - 27)
    - "Orality and Literacy" [McLuhan Program in Culture and Technology, Toronto conference; includes audiocassettes of "Ideas" a radio series of the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation based on the conference], 1986-1988 (Box 17, Folder 28-30)
    - The Technology of Writing Seminar: Transformations of the Word, Vassar, 1986-1987 (Box 17, Folder 31-32)
    - Walter J. Ong Symposium, Kansas City, 1983-1985 (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - "War as a Way of Life in Greek Classical Culture" [Georges P. Vanier memorial lectures, 1970 Oct], 1969-1970 (Box 17, Folder 34)
  - Organizations